<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The catechisme, or maner to teach children and others the Christian fayth used in all the landes and dominions that are under the mighty Prince Frederike, the Palsgraue of ye Rhone, elector of the empyre, &amp;c. Translated out of Latin into Englysh, by William Turner Doctor of Phisicke, easely to be vnderstanded and read, aswell of the people of the north cuntry, as others.</title>
            <title>Heidelberger Katechismus. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847844</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847844</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12906</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02884)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12906)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 465:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The catechisme, or maner to teach children and others the Christian fayth used in all the landes and dominions that are under the mighty Prince Frederike, the Palsgraue of ye Rhone, elector of the empyre, &amp;c. Translated out of Latin into Englysh, by William Turner Doctor of Phisicke, easely to be vnderstanded and read, aswell of the people of the north cuntry, as others.</title>
                  <title>Heidelberger Katechismus. English.</title>
                  <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richarde Iohnes, dwellyng in the vpper end of Fleetlane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1572.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Heidelberger Katechismus.</note>
                  <note>Appended, with caption title: A prayer of the repentant person taken out of Erasmus.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformed church --  Catechisms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12906:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12906:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Cathechiſme, <hi>or maner to teach Children</hi> and others the Chriſtian fayth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vſed in all the landes and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions that are vnder the mighty Prince Frederike, the Palſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rhene, Elector of the Empyre. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Latin into Englyſh, by William Turner Doctor of Phiſicke,</p>
            <p>Eaſely to be vnderſtanded and read, aſwell of the people of the North cuntry, as others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶Imprinted at London, by</hi> Richarde Iohnes, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng in the vpper end of Fléetlane. <hi>1572.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:12906:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12906:2"/>
            <head>A Cathechiſme for Children.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich is the onely comforte, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth in lyfe and in death?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANS.</hi> ¶That both concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng my ſoule and my body, whether I liue or I dye, I am not mine owne, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long only vnto my moſt faithfull Lord and ſauer Ieſus Chriſt, who with his precious blud, moſte fully makyng amendes for all my ſinnes, hath delyuered me from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Deuyll, and kéepeth mée ſo: that without the wyll of my heauenly Father, ther can not ſo much as an h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire fall from my head. Yea, and further that all things muſt ſerue for my ſaluation, wherfore he hath made mee ſure of euerlaſtyng lyfe, by his holy ſpirite, &amp; maketh mée prompt and redy from henceforth to lyue accordyng to his wyll.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶How many thinges are néedfull for thée to know, that thou mayſt come by, and enioy this cumforte, that thou mayſte both liue and dye bleſſedly?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AN.</hi> ¶Thrée: firſt, how great my ſinne and wretchednes is: The ſecond, by what meanes I may be deliuered from my ſin: The thyrd is, what thanks I owe vnto my Lorde God for my deliuerance.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:3"/>
               <head>¶The firſt parte of mans wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chednes or miſerable ſtate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>BY what meanes ſhalt thou com by the knowledge of thy wretchednes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶BY the law of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * What doth the lawe of God require of vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶That doth Chriſt in a ſhorte ſum teach vs. Mathew .xxij. and Luke .x. Thou ſhalt loue the Lorde thy God, with all thy hart, with all thy ſoule, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thy thought and with al thy ſtrength. This is the firſt, and greateſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond is lyke vnto this. Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbor as thyne owne ſelfe</p>
               <p>And the whole law &amp; prophetes hang vpon theſe two commandements.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> Canſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> kéepe al theſe things ꝑfitly?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> No for I am ready &amp; diſpoſed of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to hate God and my neighbor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Did God then make man ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward, crooked, and ſo froward?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * No, for he made him good, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the likenes of his owne ſelfe that is: en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with trew rightuuſnes &amp; holynes, that he ſhould rightly know god his maker and hartely loue him, &amp; liue for euer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, to that end that he might loue and praiſe him.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12906:3"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> * Then, from whence ſprang vp this crooked frowardneſſe of mans nature?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> ¶Of the fall &amp; diſobedience of our firſt Father and Mother, Adam &amp; Eue, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our nature is ſo made crooked &amp; naugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we al be concepued and borne in ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * Are we then all ſo wounded, that we be vtterly vnſufficient to do any good thing, and diſpoſed and ready to all vice &amp; wickednes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> Yea ſurely except that we be borne agayne by the Holy ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * Doth not God then doo wronge to man, whiles he requireth of him by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe to doo thoſe thinges which he is not able to doo, perfourme, and fulfill?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶No, for God made Adam ſo, that he might fulfill thoſe things, but he at the entiſment of the Deuyll, and by his owne ſtubborneſſe, both ſpoiled himſelfe and his after commers, of thoſe godly gifts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> Doth God let go vnpuniſhed ſuch ſtubburnes, and departing from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> * Nay, he is by horible meanes angry, both with our ſinnes that are graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in vs by nature, &amp; alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them that we afterwardes worke and doo, and the ſame he puniſheth by his moſte rightuus iudgement, with preſent and euerlaſtinge puniſhmentes as he doth pronounce.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:4"/>
               <p>Curſed is euery man that abydeth not in all thynges that are written in the Booke of the Law, that thou ſhuld kepe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶Then is not God alſo mercifull?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> He is in déede mercifull, but ſo that he is alſo rightuus, wherfore his rightuuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes requireth, that it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is done againſt the moſte highe maieſtie of God, ſhuld be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the greateſt puniſhments both of ſoule and body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>¶The ſeconde parte, of the deliuerance of man.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THen, when as by the right iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, we ar in danger both of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting paines, &amp; of ſuche that laſteth here but for a time: is there yet any way or meanes wherby we may be deliuered from theſe paynes, &amp; may be brought in fauour agayne with God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶God wyl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall make amends or ſatiſfaction vnto his rightuuſnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt néedes eyther by our ſelues, or by ſome other, content him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶Can wée by our ſelues, make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes or ſatiſfaction vnto him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> ¶By no meanes at all, but rather from day to day, do encreaſe our det.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Can any creature in heauen or in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12906:4"/> earth, whiche is only a creature, make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction, recompence, or amendes for vs and our ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> None at all: For to begyn withal, God wyl not puniſh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in any other creture which is due to be paid by man: and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer it can not (becauſe it is nothyng but a creature) abyde the wrath of God againſt ſin, and deliuer other from the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>¶QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶What maner of man is to be ſoughtout, to be our mediator and deliuerer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> He which is in déede, a very ryght man, and perfitly rightuus, and yet more mighty the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al creatures, that is, he which alſo is euen very trew God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> Why is it needefull that he ſhould be a very man, and perfitly rightuus?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> Becauſe the rightuuſnes of God requyreth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame nature which hath ſinned: ſhould pay &amp; make amends for ſin. But he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a ſinner can not pay and make amendes for other ſinners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶Why muſt he alſo be very God withall?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> That by his godly power, he may abyde the burthen of Gods wrath in his fleſh, and maye gett agayne, and reſtore vnto vs, the rightuuſnes and lyfe which we haue loſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶Who is that mediator which is both very God and very man, and perfitly rightuus withall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which is made vnto vs, the wiſdome of God, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuſnes, hallower and deliuerer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> * How knoweſt thou this?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶By the Goſpell, which God dyd open in Paradiſe, and afterward hath far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet it abroade by the Patriarches and prophets &amp; did darkly declare as it wer in a ſhaddow, by the Sacrifices and other cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the lawe, and laſt of al fulfilled, by his onely begotten ſonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> Then, is ſaluation geuen by Chriſt to all men that periſhed in Adam?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶Not to all: but onely to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by a trew faith are graffted in him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue or be pertakers of his benefites or good déedes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * What is faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> It is not onely a knowlege, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I doo ſurely aſſent to all thinges which God hath opened to vs in his worde: but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo a ſure truſt kindled in my harte by the Holy ghoſt through the Goſpell, whereby I am at peace with God, ſurely rekenyng with my ſelfe and iudgeyng that forgeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſinnes, euerlaſtyng lyfe &amp; rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſnes was geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not only to other but alſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12906:5"/> to me, that fréely by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of God, for the deſeruing of Chriſt alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * What are thoſe thinges that a Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n man muſt néedes beleue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * All thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are promiſed in the Goſpel, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſum whereof is contayned in the Creede, or articles of our faith, wherein is ſhortly conteyned as in a certayne ſhorte ſum, the cheif poyntes of the catholike and vndoubted faith of all Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶What is the Créede ye ſpeake of?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANSVVER.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beleue in God the Father almighty, maker of heauen &amp; earth. And in Ieſus Chriſte his onely begotten ſonne our Lord. Which was conceyued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt, borne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary. Suffred vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified dead &amp; buried, went downe into Hell. The thyrd day he roſe agayne from the dead. And went vp into heauen, &amp; ſitteth there at the right hand of god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almighty. From thence ſhall he come to iudge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quicke &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. I beleue in the holy goſt. That ther is a catholike church. A communion of Saints. Forgeuenes of ſinnes. The riſing agayne of the fleſh. And the lyfe euerlaſtyng. Amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> Into how many partes, is this Créede deuided?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶Into thrée partes, the firſte is of the euerlaſting father, and of our creation. The ſeconde is of the ſonne, &amp; our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or deliuerance. The thyrd is of the Holy goſt and makyng of vs holy, &amp; ſauing vs from ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶When as there is but one onely ſubſtance of God: why nameſt: thou three: the father, the ſon, and the Holy goſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶Becauſe God hath ſo opened him ſelf in his word, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe thrée ſundry perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are that one trew &amp; euerlaſtyng God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of the Father.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WHat doeſt thou beleue, when y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſayeſt, I beleue in God the father almighty, maker of heauen and earth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶I doo beleue that the euerlaſtyng Father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, which hath made of nothyng heauen and earth, and althinges that are therein: &amp; with his euerlaſtyng counſel &amp; prouiſion, vpholdeth and gouerneth al the ſame for Chriſts ſake is my God and my father, and therefore ſo truſt &amp; reſt in him, that I doo not doubt but he wyl prouide for me al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs nedful both for my ſoule and body, and that he wil alſo tourne vnto my Saluation, all the euyls
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12906:6"/> and troubles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he layeth vpon me in this troubleſome lyfe, both becauſe he can doo it, as an almighty God and will do it as a gentil Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What is the prouiſion, or proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> The almighti power of god preſent in euery place, whereby it holdeth vp, as it were with his hand, &amp; gouerneth heauen and earth and all creatures, in ſo much y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe things that grow vpon the earth, &amp; rayne, alſo faire wether, and drines, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuſnes in bearing &amp; barrennes, meat and drink, health and ſicknes, ryches &amp; pouerti and to conclude: all thinges fall and come vnto vs, not without aduice or by chance, but by his fatherly aduiſed counſell, wyll and purpoſe</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶What profite haue we by this knowlege of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god? <hi>ANS.</hi> ¶That in aduerſitie we maye be pacient and in proſperytie thankfull, and in time to come, we maye haue a very good hope in God our moſte faythfull Father, knowing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is nothyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can drawe vs awaye from his loue, for all creatures are ſo in his Power, that withoute his wyll they can not onely doo nothynge, but euen not ſo much as to ſtere or moue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:7"/>
               <head>Of the Sonne.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WWhy is the Son of God called Ieſus, that is the Sauer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe he ſaueth vs from al our ſinnes, &amp; as no ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to be craued of any other, ſo can there none be found in other, but in him alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * Then whether doo they beleue in the onely ſauer Ieſus, which ſéeke happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſaluation of ſaints, or of themſelues, or of any other thyng?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * No, For although they boaſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and reioyce in him as their Sauer in their words, yet for al that, in very ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they deny the only Sauer Ieſus, for either muſt Ieſus not be a perfit Sauer, or els al they that receaue him with a trew faith for a Sauer, haue in their poſſeſſyon in hym, all thinges neceſſary vnto ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * Why is he called Chriſtus, that is annoynted?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe he was ordayned of the Father, and was annoynted of the Holy goſt, the higheſt prophet and doctor, which hath opened vnto vs the ſecret counſel, and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of his father concerning our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption &amp; deliuerance. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hye Preiſt, who w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one ſacrifice or offring of his body
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12906:7"/> and no mo, hath bought vs agayne, and continually maketh interceſſion to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther for vs. And a Kinge which gouerneth vs with his worde and his ſpirit, and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and kepeth the Saluation which we haue gotten by hym.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶But why art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> called a chriſtian?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> Becauſ through faith I am a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſus Chriſt, and am pertaker of his an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ointing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that I confeſſe his name, &amp; geue my ſelfe vp vnto him, to be a liuing offring of thankfulnes, in this life to fight againſt ſin &amp; Sathan with a fre and good conſcience and afterwarde may hould &amp; enioy the euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt ouer al cretures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶For what cauſe is Chriſt called the onely begotten ſon of god, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are alſo the ſonnes of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe Chriſt is only the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng and natural ſon of the father euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng and we are but ſonnes choſen and taken vp of the Father of fauour, for Chriſtes ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * Why calleſt thou hym our Lord?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> ¶Becauſe he byinge agayne our bodyes and ſoules from ſinne, not with Golde nor Siluer, but with his precious bloud and deliuering them from all power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll: hath claymed vs for his owne proper ſeruants belongi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto none other Lord or maſter</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What beleueſt thou, when thou ſayeſt: he was conceiued by the holy ghoſt, and borne of the virgin Mary?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶That the ſonne of God, which, is, and abydeth trew and euerlaſting god, hath taken the very trewe nature of man, of the fleſh and bloud of the virgin Marye, by the workyng of the Holy ghoſt, that he might be alſo with al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſeed of Dauid, lyke vnto his Brethern in all thinges, ſauing onely in ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What profite takeſt thou of the holy conception and birth of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> That he is our meane or mediator, and with his innocentnes &amp; perfite holines couereth my ſinnes in the which I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, to com into the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What beleueſt thou, when thou ſayeſt he ſuffred?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶That he, all the time of his lyf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> while he was here vpon earth, but ſpecial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at his laſt time, dyd ſuffer the wrath of go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the ſin of all mankynd, that with his paſſion as one Sacrifice once for all, ſhould purchace mercy, and ſhould deliue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both our bodies and our ſoules from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng damnation, and get vs the grace o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, and rightuuſnes, &amp; euerlaſting lyfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶For what cauſe dyd he ſuffer vnder iudge Pilate?</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12906:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS,</hi> ¶That he being innocent, &amp; yet condempned before a ciuyll iudge, might deliuer vs from the ſtraight iudgement of God which we had deſerued, &amp; ſhould haue ſuffred yf Chriſt had not ſuffred this ſharp iudgement for vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Is there any other cauſe beſyde, way that he ſhuld rather ſuffer on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, then dye any other death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶Yes, there is one in déede: for by this thing I am aſſured that he toke vpon himſelf the curſe which was dew vnto me. For the death of the Croſſe was curſed of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * Why muſt Chriſt humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe euen vnto the death?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe that the iuſtice &amp; truth of God, could not be contented &amp; ſwaged for our ſinnes by ani other meanes, but by the death of the ſon of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Why was he alſo berried?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶That therby he ſhould haue ſure witneſſe that he was truely dead, and not feynedly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> But when as Chriſt dyed for vs, why muſt we alſo dye?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> ¶Our death is not a makynge of amendes for our ſinnes: but dyinge from Sinne, and a goynge into euerlaſtynge lyfe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> What profit doo we further receiue by the ſacrifice and death of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of his death our old man is crucified, kylled and berried w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, that the euyl deſires and luſtes of the fleſh ſhould not afterward rayne in vs, but that we ſhoulde offer our ſelues vnto him an offring of thankſgeueing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> * Why is it further ſaid: he went downe into Hell?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That in my greuous temptations and aſſaltes. I might ſtay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and make ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my ſelfe by this comforte, that my Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ieſus Chriſt by vnſpeakable veracious &amp; griefes, painful troubles &amp; feares of mind, into the which both before and moſt of all when he hanged on the croſſe, he was caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into: hath deliuered me from the ſorowfull griefe and paynes of Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What profite haue we by the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng agayne of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Firſte that by his ryſinge agayne he ouercame death, that he might make vs partakers of his rightuuſnes, which he had purchaſed vnto vs by his death. Moreouer, we are alſo ſtyrred vp by his power vnto a new lyfe. And the thyrde profite is, that the reſurrection of our head Chriſt, is a Pleadge and a perfite aſſurance vnto vs that we ſhall ryſe agayne in glory.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:12906:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> How vnderſtaundeſt thou this: that he is gone vp into heauen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ‡ That Chriſt (the Apoſtles lookyng on) was taken vp from the earth into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; yet ſtyll is there for our ſakes, and wyl be vntyl he ſhall com againe to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Shal Chriſt not then be with vs vntyll the end of the worlde as he hath promiſed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Chriſt is true God and true man and ſo according vnto his mans nature, he is not nowe vpon the Earth: but after his Godly nature, maieſty, grace and Spirit, he is neuer away from vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶But whether by this meanes ar the .ij. natures of Chriſt pulled in ſunder or no, if Chriſtes man hed be not where ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer his Godhed is?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ‡ Nay, for when as the Godhead of Chriſt cannot be incloſed nor holden with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any certaine compaſſe, and is preſent in euery place: it muſt néedes be a good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that his Godhead is without the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his manhead which he hath taken vpon hym, and reacheth farther and yet for all that it is faſt in the ſame, and abydeth perſonally ioyned therevnto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What fruite haue we by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goyng vp of Chriſt into Heauen?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> Fyrſt, that he maketh interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs in heauen, vnto the father. Then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee haue our fleſh in heauen, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therby we may be ſurely aſſured, as by a ſure pledge, that hereafter he wil take vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, vnto him which is our head. Thirdly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vnto vs his ſpirit i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtede of a pledge betwene him and vs, by whoſe ſtrong wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, we ſeeke not earthly things that are aboue where he is ſitting at the right hand of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Why is it further ſayd, that he is ſitting at the right hand of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe Chriſt therefore is gone vp in to heauen, to ſhew that he is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of the church by whome the father gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all thynges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What profit is this glory of our head Chriſt vnto vs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Fyrſt that through his holy ſpirite, he powreth into vs (his members) heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly gyftes, the next is, that he ſhildeth and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fendeth vs by his might, agaynſt all our enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What comfort haſt thou by the commyng agayne of Chriſt, to iudge the quicke and the dead?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That in all my perſecutions and troubles I doo looke vp to heauen holdynge my head cherefully vp for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelf ſame iudg,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12906:10"/> which purpoſedly before, dyd delyuer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the iudgement of God for me, and hath taken away all curſe from me, which ſhall caſt all his and my ennemies into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng payne, &amp; ſhal bryng me with al other choſen perſons, into the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ioys and euerlaſtyng glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of the Holy ghoſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WHat doeſt thou beleue of the holy goſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN</hi> * Firſte, that he is true and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng God, with the euerlaſtyng father and the ſonne. Secondly that he is geuen vnto me, that by true faith he maketh mée partaker of Chriſt, and all his good déedes. And thirdly, comforteth mée, and abydeth with me for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What is thy beléefe concernyng the holy and catholyke Church of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * I beleue that the ſon of God doth gather (from the beginnynge of the world vnto the end) out of hole mankynd, a choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> company by the ſpirit and the word, agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in a true faith and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> defendeth and ſaueth the ſame, and that I am one liuely member of that company, &amp; ſhal ſo abyde for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What meaneſt thou by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and felowſhyp of ſaints?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Firſte, that all and euery one that beleueth, ar in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, partakers of Chriſt and of all his good déedes, as his members and partes of his body, &amp; then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery one man ought willyngly, redely, and cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, to beſtowe the gyftes which he hath receyued, to the common profit and health of all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What beleueſt thou, of the forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenes of ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That God for the ſatiſfaction or mendes that Chriſt hath made, he hath put out the remembrance that my ſinnes, and alſo of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my crooked wickedneſſe wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I muſt fight al my lyfe time, and that he wil fréely geue vnto me the rightuuſnes of Chriſt ſo that I ſhall not come at any tyme to iudgement, to be condemned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What comfort haſt thou by the ry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſing agayne of the fleſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That not only my ſoule (after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhal departe from the body) ſhal ſtraight way be taken vp vnto Chriſt her head, but alſo that this my fleſh (rayſed vp by this power of Chriſt) ſhal be ioyned agayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſoule, and ſhall be made lyke vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorius body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What comfort takeſt thou, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> article of euerlaſtyng lyfe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN,</hi> That for as much as I fele al redy,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12906:11"/> the beginninge of euerlaſtynge lyfe in my hart: it ſhall afterwarde come to paſſe that after this lyfe, I ſhall come to full and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite bleſſednes, wherein I may prayſe god foreuer, which bleſſednes neither eye hath ſéene nor eare hath hard, neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thought of man is able to reach vnto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶But when thou beleueſt all theſe things. what profit haſt thou therby?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶That I am rightuus in Chriſt before God, &amp; an heyre of euerlaſtyng lyfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> How art thou rightuus before god?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Onely by faith or beléefe in Ieſus Chriſt, in ſo much y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> although my conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce did accuſe me, that I haue ſinned greuouſly agaynſt all the commaundements of God, and haue kepte perfitly neuer one of them, and am alſo ready and diſpoſed yet ſtyll to al euyl: yet for al that (ſo that I can receiue all theſe good déeds of Chriſt by a true fayth of my mind) the perfit ſatiſfaction or ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds makynge, the rightuuſneſſe and holyneſſe of Chriſt, is coumpted and geuen vnto mee by the only mercy of God, euen as though I had neuer done any ſin, neither any ſpot ſhould cleaue vnto me: and furthermore, as though I had fulfilled in mine own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the obedience which Chriſt hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled &amp; ꝑformed for me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Why doeſt thou hold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou art made rightuus by faith alone?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Not becauſe I doo pleaſe God with the worthyneſſe of my fayth, but becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> amendes makyng or ſatisfaction, rightuuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and holynes of Chriſte, are my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuſnes before God, &amp; I can not take holde therof, and apply the ſame vnto me by any other meanes, then by fayth alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Why can not our good workes be rightuuſnes: or at the leaſte ſome parte of rightuuſnes before God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe that rightuuſnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> muſt ſtand faſte before the iudgemente of God, muſt be in all poyntes perfite and agreeing with the word of God, &amp; al our good workes (euen the moſt holy and perfecteſt workes that we doo in this lyfe) are vnperfite and defiled with ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶How doo our good works deſerue nothynge, when as God doth promiſe that be wyll geue a rewarde for them, both in this lyfe, and in the lyfe to come?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That reward is geuen not of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing but of fauour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Doth not this learning make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be careles, Godleſſe, and of looſe liuing?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * No, for it is not poſſible but that they that are grafted into Chriſt throught fay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, ſhall brynge foorth good and thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fruits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12906:12"/>
               <head>¶Of the Sacramentes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THen, ſéeing that only faith maketh vs pertakers of Chriſt and of good dedes, from whence cometh this fayth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * From the Holy ghoſt, who kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it in our harts through the preachynge of the Goſpell, and ſtrengthneth the ſame by the vſing of the Sacraments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What are the Sacraments?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * They ar holy ſignes and ſeals ſet before our eyes, ordayned of god for that cauſe, that by them he might open vnto vs and ſettle or confirme more largely the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe of the Goſpell, that is to wyt: he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth fréely forgeuenes of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, and lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng, not only to the number of bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, but to euery one that beleueth for that onely ſacrifice of chriſt, which he made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite vpon the croſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Then, whether do both the word and Sacraments looke to that ende, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may lead our faith vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of chriſt fully ended on the croſſe, as vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und of our ſaluation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * It is ſo indéed, for the holy Ghoſte teacheth by the Goſpell (&amp; aſſureth vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtandeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only ſacrifice of chriſt, offred for vs vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12906:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶How many Sacramentes hath Chriſt ordayned in the new teſtament?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> Two. Baptiſme, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Supper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HOw arte thou warned and aſſured in Baptiſme that thou art partaker of that only Sacrifice?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe Chriſt commaunded the outward waſhing putting to this promiſe: that I am aſſurely waſhed (by his bloud &amp; the holy goſt) from al my vncleanes of my ſoule, that is from all my ſinnes, as I am outwardly waſhed with water wherby all the filthynes of the body is ſcowred away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What is it, to be waſhed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud and ſpirite of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> It is to receiue of God, forgeuenes of our ſinnes fréely for chriſtes blouds ſake, which he ſhed for vs in his ſacrifice vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, and alſo to be made new men by the Holy goſt, &amp; by his making of vs holy: to be made members of Chriſt, that thereby wée may dye from ſinne more and more, &amp; may lyue holily and vnblamedly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Where promiſed Chriſte that he wold ſo ſurely waſh vs with his bloud and ſpirite, as we are waſhed outewardly with the outwarde water of Baptiſme?</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12906:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> ¶In the .xvi. of Sainct. Marke, where as he firſte ordeyned Baptiſme, whoſe words are theſe. Go and teach all nations, and baptiſe them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the father, and of the ſon, and of the holy Goſt. And he that wyll beleue and be baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued, but he that wyll not beleue ſhall be damned. And this promiſe is reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed agayne, wher as the Scripture nameth Bapiſme the bath of the new birth, and waſhing away of ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not the outward baptiſing with water, the waſhing away of our ſinnes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * It is not: for onely the bloud of Chriſt maketh vs cleane from al ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Then why doth the holy Ghoſt cal baptiſme the bath of the new byrth, and waſhing away of ſin?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * God, not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a great cauſe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſo: to wit, not onely to teach vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as the filthines of our bodies is ſcoured away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> water, ſo likewiſe are our ſins waſhed and ſcowred away with the bloud &amp; Spirit of Chriſt: but alſo much more, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might ſicker and aſſure vs by this godly token and pledge, that we are as ſurely waſhed from our ſinnes inwardely by the inward waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as we are outwardly waſhed with the outward and ſeable water.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Ought all young ſpechleſſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be baptized</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Yea in any caſe, for when as they belonge as well vnto the couenaunt or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe, and to the chyrch of god, as they doo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are fully growne and are perfit men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: and when as forgeuenes of ſins and the Holy goſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worker of fayth, is as wel promiſed to them through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of chriſt, as to them that are full growen men and women: they ar to be grafted into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrch by baptiſme, and are to be knowne from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of vnbeleuers or infidels, as in the olde teſtament, the children of them that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leued were knowne from them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleued not, by circumciſion. In whoſe place &amp; ſted (now being taken away) Baptiſme was appoynted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of the Supper of the Lorde.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HOw art thou in the Supper of the Lord warned, aſſured, and ſickered, that thou art partaker of that onely one ſacrifice of Chriſt offred vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, and of all his good déeds?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe Chriſt hath commanded me and al faythfull men, to eat of this bred that is broken, and to drinke of this cup y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is reached vnto me in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of him
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12906:15"/> with promiſe put there to, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> firſte his bodye was aſſurely broken on the Croſſe &amp; offred for me, and his bloud as ſurely ſhed for me: as I ſe the bread of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord broken vnto me and the cuppe of the Lord reched vnto me. More ouer that my ſoule is aſwell fed vnto euerlaſtyng lyfe with his body which was crucified for vs, and with his bloud which was ſhed for vs, as I receyue with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of my body the bread and the wyne (which are tokens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; bloud of our Lord) at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of my ſheppard or elder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> What is it to eate the body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was crucified, &amp; to drinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſhed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN,</hi> * It is not onely to embrace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the hole Paſſion and death of chriſt with a ſure truſt of minde, and to get by it forgeuenes of ſinnes and lyfe euerlaſtyng: but alſo to bée ſo ioyned vnto his holy body more &amp; more through the Holy goſt which dwelleth in chriſt and in vs, that although he be in heauen &amp; we in earth, yet for al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, we are fleſh of his fleſhe, and bones of his bones, and as all the members or limmes of a manes body ar quickned or haue life of one ſoule, ſo are we quickned &amp; gouerned &amp; haue lyfe with one ſpirite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶In what place promyſed Chriſte that he would as ſurely geue his body and bloud to be eaten &amp; dronken to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleue
<pb facs="tcp:12906:16"/> as they doo eat the bread that is broken an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drinke the wyne out of the cup?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * In the place where he dyd fyrſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dayne his ſupper in theſe words. Our Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ieſus Chriſt in that night that he was be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trayed tooke the bread, &amp; after he had geue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thankes he brake it, &amp; ſayd: take eate, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is my body which is broken for you, do th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me. And ſo lykewiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> after ſupper he toke the cup, ſayinge: thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cup is the new teſtament in my bloud, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this as oft as ye ſhal drinke, in my remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance. For as ofte as ye ſhal eat this brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and drinke of this cup, ye ſhal ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Lord tyl he come .j, Cor. xj. This pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe is reherſed again by S. Paule .j. Cor x. where he ſayeth: The cup of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ksgeui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wherwith we geue thanks, is it not the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taking of Chriſts bloud? is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> breke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partaking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt? Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe we beinge many are one bread &amp; o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> body, for we are al partakers of one bread</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Are then bread and wyne made very body and bloud of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * No, but as the water of baptiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is not turned into the bloud of Chriſt, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther is the waſhinge awaye of ſinne: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> onely a token and pleadge of thoſe thinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that are ſealed into vs in Baptiſme, euen ſo is not the Breade of the Lordes Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12906:16"/> the very body of Chriſt. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, after the manner of ſpeakinge of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and the accusſtumed fashion of ſpeakyng of the Holy goſt of theſe thinges: bread is called the body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Why then doth chriſt cal bread his and the cup his bloud, or the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t through his bloud. And Paule calleth the bread and wyne, the communion or parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his body and bloud?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANSVVERE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt ſpeaketh ſo, not without great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration to wite, that he maye not onely teach vs, that euen as bread and wyne hold vp and kéepe in the lyfe of the body ſo his crucified body and his bloud that wer ſhed, are the very trewe meate and drinke of our ſoule, wherby it is nouriſhed in to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting lyfe: but alſo much more he ſpeaketh ſo, to aſſure and ſicker vs with this ſée able token and pleadge, that we are as truly pertakers of his bodye and blood by the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng of the Holy goſte, as we haue receued theſe holy Tokens in the remembrance of him, with the mouth of our body, and alſo that his paſſion or ſuffring, and his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or kéepynge of the whole lawe, are as ſurelye owers, as though we had ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our owne ſelues for our ſinnes, and had made ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to god for them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What diffrence is there betwen the ſupper of the Lord and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popyſh Meſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * The ſupper of the Lorde witnes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth that al our ſins ar forgeuen vs throg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that onely one ſacrifice that he once mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the croſſe, and that we are alſo throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the holy goſt grafted into chriſt, who afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his mans nature is onely in heauen at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right hand of the Father, and wyll be wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped ther of vs. But in the Meſſe it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> denyed that the quicke and dead haue for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geueneſſe of ſinnes through the pasſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt alone, excepte Chriſt be offred euer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day for them, by the ſacrificyng meſſ préeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Moreouer it is taughte in the Meſſe, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt is bodely preſent vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> likeneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of bread and wyne, &amp; is therefore to be wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhypped in them. And ſo the foundacion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Meſſ is nothyng els, but a denyall of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one onely ſacrifice &amp; paſſion of Ieſus chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and curſed Iolatrie, maumetry, and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippyng of by gods beſide the lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Who ought to come to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lorde?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Onely they that repent, and are very ſory that they haue angred God with their ſinnes, and yet truſt that they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuen them for Chriſts ſake, &amp; that the reſt of their weaknes &amp; vnperfitnes is couered whith his death and pasſion, who alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12906:17"/> to go forward, and grow more &amp; more in honeſt lyfe and conuerſation. But hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, falſe feigners of holynes, &amp; they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> repent not, and wyl not amend their liues, eat and drinke their owne damnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Ought we alſo to allowe them to this ſupper which ſhew them ſelues to bée faithleſſe and vngodly, both in their owne confeſſion and noughty lyfe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * No, for ſo is the couenaunt of god vnhallowed, &amp; the wrath of God is ſtyrred agaynſt the hole church. Wherfore, the church of God (accordyng to the appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt and his Apoſtles) vſing the keyes of the kyngdome of heauen, ought to hold backe ſuch from the Lords ſupper, vntyl they repent &amp; amend their maners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What are the keyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * The preachyng of the Goſpell, &amp; correction or diſcipline of the chyrch, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the kingdome of Heauen is opened to them that beleue, and is ſhut vp agaynſte them that beleue not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶How is the kingdome of heauen opened &amp; ſhut, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> * Where at the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of Chriſte we openly declare and ſhewe, all and euery Mannes Sinnes are forgeuen them by God, for
<pb facs="tcp:12906:18"/> the onely deſeruing of Chriſte, as often i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they receyue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a true fayth &amp; beléefe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promiſe of the Goſpell. Of the contrary parte, it ſheweth vnto all them that beleu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not, and to all hypocrites, feigners of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes and are wicked within, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God, and euerlaſtyng damnation hang<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth ouer their heads, accordinge to which witneſſe of the Goſpell, God wyl iudge a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> well in this lyfe, as in the lyfe to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶How is the kingdome of heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhut too, or opened, by the correction or diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipline of the Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * When as according vnto the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandement of Chriſt, they that are chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men in name, but ſhew them ſelues both i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in learning and lyfe fare from Chriſt, aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that they haue bene certayne times brothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly warned to forſake their errors, and lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their euil deedes, &amp; are preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted or ſhewed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the chyrch, or to them that are appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the chyrch vnto that office, and wyll not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bey their warning: they are ſhut out by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſame, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacraments, &amp; fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the felowſhip of Chriſts chyrch from God himſelfe, and the kyngdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt. But agayne if they promiſe to a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend their liues and do ſo in deed, they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> receaued in to the Church agayn as mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers of Chriſte and of the Chyrch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:12906:18"/>
               <head>¶The third parte is of thankfulneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WHen as we are deliuered from al our ſinnes and wretchednes without any deſeruing of vs, by the onely mercy of God for Chriſtes ſake: why ſhould we then doo good workes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Becauſe that after Chriſte hath bought vs agayne with his blood, &amp; maketh vs new me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his holy ſpirite, like vnto the ymage of himſelfe, that we hauing receued ſo many good turnes, ſhould ſhew our ſelues all our lyfe time thankefull to God, &amp; that he may be honored, &amp; afterward we euery man, maye be aſſured of his faith by his fruites, laſt of all: that we may wyn vnto Chriſt other, by our honeſte &amp; ſober lyfe or good example of liuing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Can they then not be ſaued being vnthankful, &amp; abyde ſtyl careles in ſin, and ar not turned to god fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wickednes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * In no caſe, for the ſcripture bereth witneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no vnchaſt perſon, neyther wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of ſtraing gods, neither hore maſter or aduouterers, neyther couetus men, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Théeues, nor Drunkardes, neither ſcoldyng raylers, neyther robbers, ſhall enter into the kingdome of God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶In what partes ſtandeth the turning of a man to God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * By the kylling or puttyng downe of the old man, and the quickning and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vp of the new man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What is the kylling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old man</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * It is truely and with all thy harte to be ſory that thou haſt angred God with thy ſinnes, and euery day more and more to hate them, and to flye from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What is the quikninge and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vp of the new man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> True gladnes in god thrugh chriſt, and an erneſt and redy deſyre of a man to order his lyfe accordyng to the wyl of god, of doyng of all maner of good workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> Which are good workes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Onely thei that are done in fayth accordyng to the law of God, &amp; ar wrought for that end y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God may be honored therby, and not they that are deuiſed by vs, and in our opinion (withoute the worde of God) ſeeme to be good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Which is the law of Good?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * God hath ſpoken al theſe words,</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="Ten_Commandments">
                           <p>¶The fyrſt commaundement.</p>
                           <p>I Am the Lorde God whiche hath brought thee oute of Egipte, oute of the houſe of bondage. Thou ſhalt haue no other gods in my ſight</p>
                           <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12906:19"/>
                           <p>¶The <hi>.II.</hi> commandement.</p>
                           <p>¶Thou ſhalt make vnto thee no grauen image, nor the lykenes of any thing that is in Heauen aboue, or in the erth beneth, nor in the water vnder the earth.</p>
                           <p>Thou ſhalt not bowe downe to them nor worſhip them: for I the Lorde thy God am a gelouſe God, and viſite the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children, vnto the thyrde and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhew mercy vnto thouſands in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue me, and kepe my commandemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
                           <p>The <hi>.III.</hi> commandement.</p>
                           <p>¶Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy god in vayne. For the Lorde wyl not hold hym gyltles that taketh his name in vayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</p>
                           <p>The <hi>.IIII.</hi> Remember thou kepe holy the Saboth d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>y. Syxe dayes ſhalt thou labor and doo all that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt to doo, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuenth day is the Saboth of the Lorde thy God, in it ſhalt thou doo no manner of work, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> and thy Son and thy daughter, thy man ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and thy maide ſeruant, thy cattell, and the ſtrainger that is within thy gate. For in ſix dayes the Lord made Heauen &amp; earth the Sea &amp; al that in them is, and reſted the ſeuenth day: wherfore the Lord bleſſed the ſeuenth day and halowed it.</p>
                           <pb facs="tcp:12906:20"/>
                           <p>¶The <hi>.V.</hi> Honor thy Father &amp; thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that thy dayes may be long in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land, which the Lorde thy God geueth thee.</p>
                           <p>¶The <hi>.VI.</hi> Thou ſhalt doo no murther.</p>
                           <p>¶The <hi>VII.</hi> Thou ſhalt not do aduoutry.</p>
                           <p>¶The <hi>.VIII.</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
                           <p>¶The <hi>.IX.</hi> Thou ſhalt not beare falſ wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe agaynſt thy neighbor.</p>
                           <p>¶The <hi>.X.</hi> * Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbors houſe, nor his wyfe, nor his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, nor his maid, nor his oxe nor his aſſe, nor any thyng that is his.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶How ar theſe commaundements denided?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Into two tables, of the which the former teacheth in it, foure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall behaue our ſelues towarde God. The ſecond table teacheth in ſix com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, what dewty, good déeds, and gentylnes, we owe vnto our nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> What requireth God of vs, in the fyrſt table?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That euen ſo dearely as I loue the ſaluation of my ſoule, ſo earneſtly ſhould I ſhunne and flye Idolatrye, Maumetrye, or worſhipping of falſe Gods, Witchcraft, Sorcerye, Enchauntmentes, ſuperſticion, or worſhippinge of God by other meanes then he hath taught in his worde, callyng for helpe of ſaintes or any other creatures.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12906:20"/> But that I ſhould rightly confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the onely and true God, and onely truſt in hym, and ſhould with great lowlineſſe ſubmit my ſelfe vnto hym, and looke for all good thinges of hym alone, and that with all my harte and with all the deſires of the ſame: loue hym, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence worſhyp and honor hym ſo much, that I had leauer forſake all Creatures, then to doo any thyng contrary to his wyll.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶What is Idolatry?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> * It is, in the ſtede of one God, or beſide hym that is the true God, who hath opened and ſhewed hymſelfe playnely and clearely in his worde, to feygne, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e or haue any thynge wherein thou beleueſt or put teſt thy hope in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶What requyreth the Seconde comaundement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That we ſhould not ſhew, ſet out, or expreſſe God, by any Image or figure, neither ſhould we worſhyp hym any other way then he hath commanded in his word hymſelfe to be worſhipped.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Whether the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought any Images or lykneſſes of thyngs to be made?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * God neither ought, neither can by any meanes be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfeited, ſhewed or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clard, by ani caſter, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, keruer or payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="tcp:12906:21"/> and although they be ſuffred to expreſſe creatures, as herbes, trées, fiſhes, &amp; byrdes, and ſuch lyke: yet God forbiddeth their ymages to be made or had, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through them we ſhould worſhip or honor God, or geue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any worſhip, or outward reuerence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Whether ought images to bée ſuffred to ſtand in churches to be lay mens bookes or no?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * No no. For it is not ſéemely that we ſhould be wiſer then God who willeth that his church ſhould be taught with the liuely preaching of his word, and not with dumme images.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What doth God ordayne in the thyrd commaundement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That we ſhould not onely, not vſe his name ſpightfully and vnreuerently in bannyng, curſing, forſweareing, and raſhly without a iuſt cauſe in any maner of ſweareing at all, neither ſhould we be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of theſe horible and wicked ſinnes, either by holdyng of our peace, or in win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng at them, but that we ſhould vſe that holy name of God no otherwiſe but with deuocion, reuerence, and worſhip, that he may be worſhipped and honored in all our words &amp; déeds w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a true and ſtedfaſt confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpon his name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> Is it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo greuus a ſin, to diſhonor
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12906:21"/> the name of God in ſwereyng and in cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that God is alſo angry with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyll not (as much as lyeth in them) hinder forbid and let it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Surely it is the moſte greuus ſin, neither is there any that angreth and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth hym more, then the ſpightful miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing of his name. Wherefore it was his wyl that it ſhuld be puniſhed with death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> May not a man ſomtime godly and lawfully, ſweare by the name of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN</hi> * He may. Either when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſtrate Gods officer requireth or commandeth a man to ſweare, or other wiſe when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, that by this mene a man may get credit, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth may be proued &amp; ſtabliſhed therwith that therby God may be glorified and prayſed, &amp; men may be holpen therby. For ſuch a lawfull oth is aproued as holy by the word of God, &amp; therfore it was well vſed of the fathers both in the old and new Teſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Is it lawful for a man to ſweare by ſaintes or other creatures?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> No, For a lawfull oth is the calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or inuocatio of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he (as onely the knower of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecretes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harte) may geue witneſſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, &amp; puniſh the ſwerer (yf wittingli he ſweare falſly) but this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor is to begeuen vnto no creature.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What hath God commaunded i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the fourth commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Firſt, that the ſeruing in the offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of preching and miniſtring of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and that the ſcooles ſhould be kepte, main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyned and prouided for, that I on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hally<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day and at other times when the chyrch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (for ſome neceſſary cauſe) gathred togethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould ioyne my ſelfe vnto that holy felow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip, to heare the worde of God diligentl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and héedefully, and to vſe the ſacramentes, and ioyne my prayers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayers, and geue ſomthyng accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to my riche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto the poore, and afterwarde for all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lyfe time, kepe halliday and forbeare from all yll déeds, geueyng place, and granting vnto God that through his holy ſpirite, he may work his works in me: &amp; ſo may begin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſaboth or hallyday in this lyfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What inioyneth God vs to doo it the fift commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That we ſhould geue dew hono<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſhewe faithfulnes to our Fathers an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mothers, and to al that ar gouernors ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vs, and ſhould ſubmite our ſelues with al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conuenient obedience, vnto their faithfull commandements &amp; chaſtnings &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld ſuffer &amp; beare w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their vices &amp; maners, euer thinking this in our mind, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god wyll go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne and guyde vs by their hand.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:12906:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What doth God require in the ſixt commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> * That I ſhould doo no iniurie wrong or reproch to my neighbour neither with my wordes, geſture or outwarde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauur, either by my ſelfe, or by any other man, hate hym, hurt hym, or kyll hym: but to leaue &amp; geue ouer al the deſire of reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vnto God, nether that I ſhould hurte my ſelf, nor caſt my ſelf wittingly int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any ieoperdy. Wherefore God hath armed the Maieſtrate his officer with the ſword, that there ſhould no murder be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Doth this commandement onely forbyd manſlaughter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Almighty God by forbiddyng of murder, teacheth that he hateth the roote &amp; begining of murder: anger, enuy, hatred, and deſire of wreaking or reuengyng, and that he taketh al theſe things for murder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> Is it enough for vs, to kyl no man, by thoſe meanes that are before reherſed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * It is not enough. For when as God forbiddeth anger, enuy, and hatred: he requireth that we ſhoulde loue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borres as our ſelues, ſhould vſe toward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gentylnes, myldnes, mekenes, pacience &amp; mercy, and to turne away or ſtop (aſmuche as lyeth in vs) ſuch thyngs as may be hurt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And finally y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould ſo be
<pb facs="tcp:12906:23"/> mynded toward them, that we ſhould goo euen vnto our enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> What is the meanyng of the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That God defieth al filthines, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> therfore we ought alſo to hate it, &amp; vtter to defie it, &amp; that we ſhoulde liue contrar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto all vncleanes, temperatly, ſoberly chaſtly, both in holy wedlocke and alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſingle lyfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Doth God forbyd no more in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commandement, but aduoutri, fornicatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſuch kyndes of filthynes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * When as our bodyes &amp; ſoules at the chyrches or Temples of the holy Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the wyll of God is, that we ſhoulde ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them both cleane, as hallowed vnto hym and therfore vtterly forbyddeth all déedes ſignes, tokens, geſtures and wordes, filth deſires, and what ſo euer intiſeth a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What doth God forbyde in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eyght commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> Not only ſuch thefts and robber it as the common officers doo puniſh: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnderſtandeth vnder the name of theft, a crafty fetchs, drifts, ſubtyl means &amp; ways whereby we hawke &amp; lye in wayte, to tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other mens goods from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or labor to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs, either by might or viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12906:23"/> or by any falſe pretence of right, as though we had a iuſte tytle to them, and yet haue none at all, Such meanes ar falſe weights falſe yeardes, elles, and falſe meaſures, counterfeit and vnlawful ware, counterfet and vnlawfull money, vſurye, &amp; al vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes and wayes that God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydden to get a mans lyuyng withal. Héer vnto may be put and ioynd all couetuſnes and vnthrifty and prodigal powryng out, and ſpendyng and waſtyng of Gods gifts, and euyll vſing of the ſame,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What are thoſe thinges, whiche God commandeth here?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> That as much as is poſible, I ſhuld helpe and increaſe the goods and profite of my neighbor. And that I ſhould doo ſo vnto hym, as I wold he ſhould doo vnto mée, and that I ſhould doo my worke earneſtly, truly and faithfully, that I mai therby be able to releue and helpe, them that haue néede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What requireth the nynth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That I ſhall not beare falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes agaynſt any man, neither falſly turne the meanyng of any mans wordes, nether ſhal backbyghte any man, or ſpightfully rayle agaynſte any man, neyther ſhall raſhly without the ſhewynge of a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cauſe, condemne any man.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:24"/>
               <p>But with al the meanes that I can, I ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſlye and eſchew al kynd of lyes &amp; deceipts as the proper works of the deuyll, except <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be diſpoſed to ſtere vp agaynſt me, the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous wrath of God. In iudgments &amp; othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> matters I ſhall folowe it that is true, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtedfaſtly &amp; fréely, tel &amp; confeſſe the matte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as it is indéede, &amp; morouer I ſhall (as muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as I can) defende and increaſe, the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> name, fame, and credit of my neighbors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> What forbiddeth the .x. comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> That our hartes ſhould not be mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued or ſtirrid vp, with ſo much as with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leaſt thought or deſire, agaynſt any of god commandementes, but that we ſhall ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and defy at all times, al kynd of ſinne, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhal delyte our ſelues in all rightuuſnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Can they that are turned to Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kepe perfitly, &amp; fully, theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> ¶No, For euen the holyeſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all men (as longe as they lyue héere) ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but ſmal beginings of this obedience. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet go ſo farre, that they earneſtly (with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feigned deſire) begin to liue, not onely a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordyng vnto ſom of theſe commandem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, but accordyng to al the commandeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Why wyll God then that hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> law ſhuld be ſo erneſtly &amp; ſharply preched
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12906:24"/> when there is no man in this lyfe, that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble to kepe it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Fyrſt, that all the time of our lyfe we ſhall confeſſe and acknowleadge how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reatly we are diſpoſed of nature to ſin, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o thereby that we more greedely, and with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greatter deſire, call for the forgeuenes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur ſins, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould always be occupied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this, that we alwayes be thinking and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecording with our ſelues of godlines, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al vpon the Father for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſte, that we may be renewed &amp; faſhioned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the lykeneſſe of god euery day more and more, vntyll at the length, after that we be departed out of this lyfe, we may with ioy and gladnes get the full perfitnes, that is purpoſed, ſet foorth, and requyred of vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Of Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WHy is prayer neceſſary for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANS.</hi> * Becauſe it is the chiefe parte of that thankfulnes that God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of vs, and alſo becauſe God onely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them his grace and holy ſpirit, who ar thinges neceſſary of hym, with true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned gronynges, and geueyng thankes for ſuche benefytes as they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12906:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What things ar required in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prayer which ſhal pleaſe God, and be he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That we ſhould aſke of the onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true God whiche hath opened him ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his worde (al thoſe thinges whiche he hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commanded to be axed, with a true deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the harte, and an inwarde felyng of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beggerly need and wretchednes, &amp; caſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelues downe humbly and lowly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Gods maieſtie, leane to this ſure fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dation, that although we be vnworthy, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhal ſurely be hard for Chriſtes ſake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he hath promiſed vs in his word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶What are thoſe thynges that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> commaundeth to be axed axed of hym?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Al thinges that are neceſſary b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for body and ſoule, which our Lorde Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſte conteineth in his prayer that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath taught vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Which is that prayer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANSVVER.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr father whiche art in he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, halowed be thy nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Thy kyngdome come. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wyll be done in earth as it in heauen. Geue vs this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our dayly bread. And forge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vs our dettes, as we forgeue our dette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And lead vs not into temptation. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12906:25"/> deliuer vs from euyl. For thine is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome, the power &amp; the glorye, for euer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Why doth Chriſt command that we ſhould call God our father?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> That he might ſtyrre vp in vs euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the very beginning of our prayer, ſuche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euerence as is méet for the ſonnes of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd a bolde truſt toward God which is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the ground of our prayer, to wyt, that God throgh Chriſt is made our father, and wyll much leſſe denye vnto vs thoſe things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat we axe of hym with a true faith: then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur earthly father wyl deny vnto vs, erthly thyngs. <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Why is it ſayde fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whiche art in heauen?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That we ſhoulde not thynke to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ylely, bacely, or earthly, of his heauenly maieſtie, and that we ſhould looke for, and wayte of his almightyneſſe, for all things whatſoeuer ar neceſſary for our ſoules and bodyes. <hi>QVESTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶Which is the firſt pitition or axyng?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Halowed be thy name, that is to ſay: at the beginninge, graunt vs that we may rightly know thee, and worſhip praiſe and honor thy almightines, thy wiſedome, thy rightuuſnes and gentylnes, thy mercy and thy truth and afterward, purpoſe and driue al our life, our thoghts words &amp; deeds
<pb facs="tcp:12906:26"/> vnto this ende, thy moſt holy name be n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blaſphemed, or euyll ſpoken of for vs, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rather be hyghly honored and prayſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Which is the ſecond peticion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Thy kyngdome come. That is g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerne vs ſo with thy worde and ſpirit, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we maye humble and ſubmite oure ſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more and more vnto thée, kepe and incre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thy church, deſtroy the works of the deuy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and all power that lifteth it ſelfe agaynſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy Maieſty, diſapoynt and make voyd an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of none effect, al he counſelles that ar t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken agaynſt thy worde, vntyl thou may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (at the length) reigne and rule ful &amp; perfit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when as thou ſhalt be all in all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Which is the thyrd peticion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Thy wyll be done in earth as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in heauen. That is grant that we and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men (renounſing and forſakyng our ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wylls) may be obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, redyly bent, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out any grudge vnto the kepyng of thy w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is onely holy, and that ſo euery o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of vs, may fulfyll and doo the office that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> appoynted vnto vs, faithfully &amp; cherefull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as the Angels doo in Heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Which is the fourth peticion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN</hi> Geue vs this day our dayly bread. That is, geue vnto vs al thyngs which néedfull &amp; neceſſary for this lyfe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them we may knowledge &amp; confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12906:26"/> art onely the well, out of the which al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes doth ſpryng, and that all our care and labor, &amp; alſo thy owne gyfts, are vnlucky and noyſome vnto vs, except thou doo bleſſe them, &amp; geue them increaſe. Wherefore graunt vs to turne away our truſt from all creatures, and to put it onely in thée.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Which is the fifte peticion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Forgeue vs our dettes, as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue our detters. That is, for Chriſts blud ſake, lay not to our charge that are wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinners, all our ſins: and that crooked frowardnes which cleueth in vs ſtyl, euen as we doo feele this wittneſſe of thy grace in our hartes, that we intende &amp; purpoſe ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to forgeue vnfeignedly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our mind, all them that haue hurte or gréeued vs, or haue done vs any wrong.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QV.</hi> ¶Which is the ſixt peticion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * Lede vs not into temptacion. But deliuer vs from euyl. That is, becauſe we are ſo féeble &amp; weake of nature, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, one minute of an houre without help, ſtand ſtedfaſtly and not be ouer throwne, and our moſt greuous enemies, the deuyl, the world, and our owne fleſh, vnſeſſably do fight againſt vs. Thou O our almighty father, hold vp and ſtay vs, and ſtrengthen vs by thy might of thy Holy ghoſte, that we fal not downe and bée ouercommed in
<pb facs="tcp:12906:27"/> this ſpirituall fight, but ſo long we maye ſtoutly withſtand them, vntyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye get at length, the whole victory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶How maketh he an end of this prayer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * For thine is the kyngdome, the power, and the glory, for euer. Amen. That is to ſay, we are all theſe thinges of thée, becauſe thou art both our kyng, &amp; art almightye, and both wyll, and can geue al theſe things vnto vs, and theſe thinges do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we therefore craue of thée, that by them, al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onor, glory, &amp; worſhip, ſhould come vnto thy holy name and not to vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVE.</hi> ¶What meaneth this worde, Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AN.</hi> * That the matter is ſure and ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of all doubt, and that my prayer is much more ſurely ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of God, then I doo feele i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my hart that I deſyre it to be granted.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>
               <hi>¶FINIS.</hi>
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:12906:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Prayer of the repentant perſon taken out of the workes of Eraſmus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt high creator and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of all thinges, when as I cal to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance how greatly I haue ſtirred vnto anger thi maieſty with my ſins: I doe defye mine owne fooliſhnes. When &amp; wey with my ſelfe how gentle &amp; liberal a father I haue forſaken, I loth and crye out againſt mine vnkyndnes. When I mark, in how wretched a bondage I haue caſt my ſelfe, flyinge from ſuch liberty and fréedome of the ſpirit that I had, I doo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem my madnes, and in alpoints miſlyke my ſelfe. Neither is there any other thing that appeareth before mine eyes, but Hell fyre, &amp; deſperation, while thy vnavoydable rightuuſnes in puniſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of ſin doth ſo mak my conſcience affrayde. But of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part, when I conſider thy vnmeſurable and infinite mercy, which accordyng to the witnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet) paſſeth al thy works and whereby thou (after a certaine maner) art greater then thy ſelfe, &amp; when as thou art greteſt of al other, by and by, a certaine pleaſaunt breath of hope, doth refreſhe my mynd agayne. For why ſhould I deſpayre
<pb facs="tcp:12906:28"/> to get forgeuenes of ſinnes of him whiche ſo oft in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bokes of the Prophets doth fréely of hym ſelf, cal ſinners to repentance: cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he wyl not haue the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but that he ſhould liue: and further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, becauſe forgeuenes is alwayes in a redines to be graunted of thée, to them that are penitent &amp; ſory for their ſinnes, as thy only begotten ſon hath declared oft times by diuers lykeneſſes: as by it of the loſte péece of mony, that was loſt and founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. And of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Shep y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was brought hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agayne, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mans ſhoulder. But more euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimilitude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prodigal ſon, whoſ image I do acknowledg ꝑfitly to be in me For moſt wickedly I haue left my moſt louing Father, and haue wickedly waſted away his ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And while I folow th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> luſts of my fleſh, and forget thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes: I haue wrapped my ſelfe into the moſte filthy bondage of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; am brought vnto extreme beggerlynes, neither can I tel to whom I ſhuld flye for ſuccor, but vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him from whome I ran away. Let thy mercy receiue hym, makynge ſupplication vnto thée: whom y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt hether to gentylly ſuffred, goynge aſtraye. I am vnworthy to lyfte vp mine eyes to thée béeinge in heauen, or to call thée by the name of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but I beſech thée vouchſaue to turne
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12906:28"/> thy eyes vnto mée, for thy countinaunce maketh a dead ſinner to lyue agayne, and hym that is loſte to come home agayne too repentance, for I ought to thank thy loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng countinance, euen for that that I miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke my ſelfe. Thou haſt vouchſafed to looke vpon me while I went a ſtray from thee. For thou haſt geuen me eyes to ſée in what miſerable ſtate I was, &amp; thou came forth and met mée, and did breth into mée, the memory &amp; deſire of innocencie. I beyng a bondman, worthy all kynd of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſire not to be embraced &amp; kyſſed of thée. I deſire not a long gowne and a ring, the badges &amp; tokens of my olde dignitie which I haue caſt away. I make not ſupplicacion that thou ſhould receiue me vnto the honor of thy Sonnes, but it ſhall be innough for me, yf that thou receiue me among the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the moſte vile runnegate bondmen, hauing their backs al ful of ſcars, by iuſtly deſerued often beating: but at the leaſt, I may cleaue vnto thee with ſom part of thy ſeruants, as in thy houſe are many dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng places. It ſhall not gréeue mee to bée numbred in this lyfe among the vileſt, to bée tormented by repentaunce, to bée made foule with wéepyng: ſo that I be not departed from thée for euer. I beſéech thée father, &amp; deſyre thée thrugh the death of thy
<pb facs="tcp:12906:29"/> onely welbeloued ſonne, let mée haue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpirit whiche may cleanſe my harte, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrengthen mée with his grace, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neuer fal backe agayne by fooliſh vnheede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fullnes, thither from whence I am called backe agayne by thy gentilnes. So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:12906:29"/>
            <head>¶ A TABLE OF THE contentes of this booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the only comforte, both in this lyfe and at our departure. 2.</item>
               <item>Of the wretchednes of man. ibidem.</item>
               <item>That we haue no frée wyll or choyſe of our ſelues. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Of the wrath of God for our ſinnes 3.</item>
               <item>Of the mercy of God. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Of the rightuuſnes, or ſtreight pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Of the deliuerance of man. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Of ſatisfaction or makyng amends for ſin. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Who is our meane or mediator. 4.</item>
               <item>What faith is. ibidem.</item>
               <item>What things ar neceſſary to beleue. 5.</item>
               <item>Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> créed, or articles of our faith. ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>Of the prouidence of God. 6.</item>
               <item>Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> going downe of chriſt to hell. 8.</item>
               <item>That onely faith iuſtifieth. 11.</item>
               <item>Of the Sacraments. 12.</item>
               <item>Of Baptiſme. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Of the Lords ſupper. 13.</item>
               <item>That Chriſt is not really, bodily, or fleſhly, in the ſupper. 15.</item>
               <item>Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of heauen 16.</item>
               <item>Wherfore we muſt doo good works. 17.</item>
               <item>Of mortification or kyllyng or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde man
<pb facs="tcp:12906:30"/> and of our fleſhly luſts &amp; deſires. ibid</item>
               <item>The .x. commandements. ibide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>What is Idolatry.</item>
               <item>Of inuocatian, or callyng vpon ſaints for helpe. ibide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt the vſe of Images.</item>
               <item>That the commandements can not be kepte fully or perfytly</item>
               <item>Of prayer,</item>
               <item>The expoſition of the Lords prayer. or Pater noſter. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer taken out of the workes of Eraſmus Rot.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> end of Fléetlane: by Richard Iohne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ar to be ſold at his Shop ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng to the Southweſt Dore of S. Paules Church.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>R. I.</head>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Johns</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
